this is angaya book of 11 suta number n
called wand at one time the Buddha was staying
wand at one time the Buddha was staying
at natia in the brick house then
venerable Su went went up to the Buddha
bowed and sat down to one side the
Buddha said to him Su meditate like a
Thor bread not like a wild CT so like a
Thor bread would be a well tamed horse
and a wild cult would be like an untamed
horse and how does a wild CT
meditate uh a wild Colt tied up by the
feeding truff meditates f f so like he's
just concerned with his food with the
hay that that's given to him why is that
because it doesn't occur to the wild CTS
tied up by the feeding truff what t ask
will the horse trainer have me do today
how should I respond tied up by the
feeding truff it just meditates f
f in the same way take an take a certain
untrained person who has gone to the
forest the root of a tree or an empty
Hut their mind is overcome and mired and
sensual desire and they don't understand
as it is he escape from a risen sensal
desire harboring sensual desire
internally they meditate and contemplate
and citate and r minate their mind is
overcome by a will indol indolence and
lethargy restlessness and anxiety doubt
harboring doubt internally they meditate
and contemplate and citate and ruminate
they meditate dependent on earth water
fire and air they meditate dependent on
the extent of Infinite Space infinite
Consciousness nothingness or neither
perception nor
non-perception they meditate dependent
on this world or the other world they
meditate dependent on what is seen heard
thought cognized attained sought or
explored by the mental faculty that's
how an untrained person meditates and
how does a Thor bread meditate uh a fine
Thor bread tied up by the feeding truff
doesn't meditate fod fodder why is that
because it occurs to the Fine thorough
bread tied up by the feeding Tru what
task will the horse trainer has have me
do today how should I respond tied up by
the feeding Tru it they they don't
meditate for water f for that fine
thorough bread regards the use of the
goat as a debt a bond a loss a
misfortune in the same way take a
certain fine thoroughbread person who
has gone to the forest the riv a tree or
an empty Hut their mind is not not
overcome admired and sensal desire and
they understand as it is the escape from
a risen sensual desire their mind is not
overcome by a will indolence and
lethargy restlessness and anxiety doubt
they don't meditate the dependent on
earth water fire and air they don't
meditate dependent on the extent of
Infinite Space infinite Consciousness
nothingness or neither perception nor
non-perception they don't meditate
dependent on this world or the other
world they don't meditate dependent on
what is seen heard thought cognized
attained sought or explored by the
mental faculty yet they do meditate when
a fine thorough bre meditates like this
the gods together with Indra Brahma and
the progenitor worship them from afar
homage to you all Thor bread homage to
you Supreme among men we don't
understand what your meditation depends
on so this is basically the most
important part so
part so
um there we have it the Buddha is
explicitly advising against any type of
absorption meditation so um
what does it
mean we can start with
um description or discussion of what
mindfulness is
because often times
mindfulness nowadays is regarded
precisely as that as a type of
absorption on one thing or or uh at
least sort of focused attention on one
thing usually the breath or bodily
Sensations body scanning and uh even
thoughts which all of that is included
by what the suta said what is sensed
cognized thoughts explored by the mental
faculty that's like literally anything
yeah and people think then samadi is
like absorption and so yeah in the noble
a path it talks about Sati mindfulness
and then samadi and so people think
mindfulness is about focusing on
something which then naturally has to
result in the Samar which is the
absorption of that thing fixed state
when the when the focusing has been
consumated yeah yeah so yeah what let's
say um mindfulness so if it isn't about
um mindfulness so if it isn't about
focusing if it isn't about just looking
at what's in front of you like the wild
cult is just looking at the hay that's
in front of him and it's instead it says
the Thor bread wonders about something
that's broader than what's in front of
it yeah he still meditates but not on it
as it says there earth water fire air or
what is being predes basically yeah so
so you can see the list is is when you
see these kinds of list in sutas like in
maim Manaya 1 where list basically every
possible permutation of
anything that means there is
no object or thing that would be good
for you to focus focus on the right
mindfulness is the opposite direction of
that which is exactly what what it says
the the the
horse Takes a step back from what's
actually going on and uh discerns a
broader context and that's the principle
of of mindfulness
so and I think people often don't
realize that they do have mindfulness or
a certain principle of
mindfulness underlying their everyday
actions which is what allows them to
function um but
nevertheless because of the views
nowadays it gets conceived as this
basically artificial contrived practice
that nobody would do unless you tell
them mhm um is what mindfulness is
whereas sometimes you already have
mindfulness and you may not even realize
it because you think it's something else
yeah maybe we should start there that
mindfulness is not something that you
fully have to create from strch yeah but
it's basically already a structural
aspect of experience that needs to be
understood and developed right so so um
I thought of giving an an example so
when you have
um when you let's say go to a
supermarket and uh you know what you
have to buy it's one specific thing and
you're supposed not to spend too much
time in the supermarket you're supposed
to be go somewhere else and there's a
certain deadline there time constraint
so there there are going to be lots of
distractions in the
supermarket and um you would have at the
back of your mind a sort of perspective
of uh this is what I need to buy and um
I need to be out of here in 15
minutes and even though your your
perceptions are occupied with the things
that you're seeing in the supermarket
which might not be the thing that you
are specifically looking for you're
walking around looking through the
different aisles and whatnot and
um your perception is like the these are
the fod like the wild horse is what's in
front of you the things that you're
seeing but at the back of your mind you
have this context of why you're actually
there and so that's what actually
allowing you to you know when you see I
don't know something that you would have
otherwise become um distracted by yeah
captivated by captivated by uh you don't
because you have that broader context in
mind even though you did see the
perception it's not that you sort of
like BL blinded yourself so um that is
actually a principle of mindfulness and
you realize it's not even something
you're doing it's like it's not not even
cuz if it were on the level of what
you're choosing to attend to then
immediately when you choose to attend to
the things that are in front of you
which are not what you're looking for
you would lose your mindfulness uhhuh
yeah that's right so that already shows
that these are two levels happening in
your experience and at the same time at
the same time and that level where the
memory is or the the context is that it
that doesn't even require effort it
requires a negative effort basically of
not allowing yourself to as you said get
captivated by anything specific because
if you allow your allow that to happen
then that's when the memory will fade
and you will find oh 10 minutes have
passed by and I was just you know
grabbing all this other stuff that I
didn't actually need
so um that's a that's a basic form of
mindfulness that that uh everybody would
have and you would realize some people
have such little amount of mindfulness
that they couldn't even fulfill that
type of task um they would Bas reliably
they would basically forget why they
went to the grocery store come back home
with a bag of stuff do even contain what
they what they went to the goer store
for to begin with yeah yeah so
um the the the focusing
direction is like there is some
overlap with you being Mindful and you
being focused but the overlap is
actually quite
small um because yes if you every second
try to focus on the thought of what
you're what you have to get technically
yes you won't forget but the you're not
actually understanding that the memory
of the the context of why you're in the
supermarket that actually endures at a
different level of your attention so
you're overdoing the practice so you don't need
overdoing the practice so you don't need
to collect 100 times when you when you
have only 10 15 minutes in the
supermarket what it is that you want to
get that is that is not how it would
ordinarily work yeah yeah but it's it's
also because of these views that get
imposed over over the practice which is uh
over over the practice which is uh
mainly originated from the Abid and the
commentary is that the mind is made of
made up of these discret moments that
follow individually you know there's
nothing endures for more than one month
mind moment and so the view then is
every mind moment needs to have
mindfulness in it like me actively doing
that mindfulness because
otherwise I will forget yeah that's a
rather that results in a rather neurotic
take on what mindfulness is yeah so you
would realize that type of mindfulness
you will never be able to have it always
you will you only be able to have it in
periods where um you're basically not
functioning mhm as a person like you're just fully
mhm as a person like you're just fully
um sitting
down absorbed dedicated to nothing else
but the practice and technically from
that point of view every other moment of
your life as a Buddha said someone who
is not mindful is as if dead so that
means like 90% of your time unless
you're in Retreat always you're being
heedless because you're not mindful if
that's what mindfulness
yeah whereas if we understand it in this
way which by the way that was obviously
a mundane example of mindfulness but I
just gave the example of the supermarket
but if we now take it on a more um
accurate level of of the mind and uh
actually make it relevant to the to
freedom from suffering you could see
well you would have the
same um recollection of let's say not
acting out of un wholesome
states by Body speech and mind not
breaking the precepts yeah we should
clear up that there's this difference
between focusing on things in front of
view and recollecting context which is
what the mindfulness is as we have now
established but then we need to give
some content quote unquote to what is
the right context yeah so that that's
the the principle of
the the establishing of mindfulness is
that you do need to attend to it for a
moment like you you can't just expect
that the context will be already there
it's more like setting it up and then it
endures on its own so the same with this
you do have to for a moment think about
okay I am supposed to leave the
supermarket in 15 minutes it's not that
if you don't think about it it will be
there on its own but once you think
about it it just sort of floats there on
its own and you don't need to be
constantly now if you find yourself
getting distracted then you need to
think about it again oh I'm supposed to
get out of here and 9:15 or whatever so
then you bring it back but throughout
the time where that context was there
that mindfulness was there floating on
its own you don't need to
be like CU that would actually distract
you like imagine if you if you're just
totally uh going in that in that
direction of trying to remember it every
second you won't even be able to pay
attention to what's happening in front
so so you may find actually sort of the
product that you're looking for and you
can read the the label pay attention to
that trying to understand what it says
the label of the product right and and
you're not directly attending to that
context but that doesn't mean that you
have lost your mindfulness on that
occasion it is only when you then stray
away from your aim that you would have
lost it and and have to bring it back so
you can basically actually attend to all
sorts of other things which is not in
conflict with being mindful which is
recollecting that context yeah so in the
same way you would have for example a
context of I should not act out of a
wholesome state so I shouldn't break the
precepts and you would go through your
life and many times you would have
moments where you are factually like you're
where you are factually like you're
going to work or something you you can't
like you have to pay attention to what
you're doing you can't be thinking about
this the whole time but you you can
still be mindful of that and and how
would you know that you've lost your
mindfulness well when you catch yourself
making an intention to do something that
was that you had previously determined
not to do then you know I lost my
mindfulness the thing is you cannot have
like um you cannot have like an external
point of view where you see like the
mindfulness enduring and then this is the second
enduring and then this is the second
where it's faded that's not how it works
cuz that back up and then right there
you pick it back up you saw yeah yeah no
no that requires that would require you
to have an external perspective to your
own experience and mindfulness is quite
the opposite mindfulness is like it
comes before your point of view so you
can't like watch it as an object that's
why it's saying like the bride
meditation doesn't depend even on what's
explored by the mental faculty what's
explored by the mental faculty comes
second to the mindfulness if it's
established properly so you won't even
be able to like watch it um fading it's
just you find
yourself after the fact you can't even
Trace like how long how much time past
you find yourself oh I lost my
mindfulness because I was about to do
something break a precept with whereby
um even though I had determined I
wouldn't do it that then you have to
restart it but uh the point is you don't
develop a view that it's about
constantly having it there it's about
restarting it or refreshing it when you
lose it m and the funny thing is there
is a certain sense of of the direction
of mindfulness that's uh embedded into a
lot of the uh modern practices like the
the noting for example like you know
when you're doing something and then
you're telling yourself sitting sitting
sitting walking walking walking bending
bending bending uh yeah the thing is
like if you were totally U oblivious to
that broader context of like what your
body is doing and then you bring your
mind back to that that is a direction of
mindfulness but the thing is if you now
okay you established it but now you keep
attending to it every second then now
you're overdoing it because the point
was not to to like you actually lost the
mindfulness as a result of doing that
because you became absorbed the whole
point of the mindfulness should have
been okay I am sitting and now that sort
of
peripheral um image or idea endures in your mind
um image or idea endures in your mind
while it's now like we can do it right
now for for example like um okay so I
remember that I am here sitting down
even while I'm talking my body is in
this position and
position and
then now I'm thinking about other things
I'm not particularly thinking about my
body sitting down but that memory is
still there enduring and that until that
body changes posture for example yeah so
then yeah I haven't thought about it I
still haven't forgotten about the fact
that I'm sitting and so that's the
principle like um so there might be it
so ordinarily when one hasn't come
across the bu teaching mindfulness is
already in a small degree there as you
said in in the beginning as a structural
principle but then people are not
developing it but on account of wrong
instructions and wrong ideas those
people who are developing mindfulness
there's a high chance that they might
actually overdo it right so now a simly
occurs to me as as well just to continue
with the grocery store so suppose
somebody has to buy something in the
shop they they need to walk there um and
they say well let's this is the wrong
type of mindfulness but just as an as an
illustration and they say let's use this
10minute walk to the grocery store to
practice mindfulness and then they pay
attention to every time they put their
right foot on the ground and every time
they put their left foot on the ground
and they actually pay attention every
time they put their foot on the ground
for the next 10 minutes they don't miss
a single step but then they find that
they actually walked to their friend's
house and are about to ring the doorbell
there now did that person now practice
mindfulness correctly or not right most
people might say yeah because you know
you were actually you know walking
walking feeling every time my foot on
the ground I felt it there so I was
there with my mind but the whole point
is you were too concerned with that
narrow specific exercise failing to
realize that you were just going to do
that because you had something more
important to do namely to get that item
from the gooster store which somebody
has now completely spaced out and they
ended up doing doing doing something
different yeah and and also um you often
sometimes even hear the view
that like when
you oh I was meditating and I I totally
forgot what was happening like my my
concentration was so good that like I
didn't even realize that time was
passing by or something I just totally
forgot and that's regarded as a good
thing whereas mindfulness is actually
awareness it's it's quite the opposite
direction like you're so aware that you
can't even
Overlook anything like but on the on the
on that level of your actions your
attention the mindfulness precedes the
attention so essentially like it would
be impossible for you to to say
something like I forgot where I was or
something um yeah because you would be
because if attention is secondary you
you would have a memory or or you would
be able to recollect what it is that you
were attending to if the mindfulness is
more fundamental than whatever it is
that you're attending to yeah right yeah
and and uh that's the fundamental
purpose of mindfulness of the body which
is um is like the most popular one um
because it does ironically or
unfortunately allow for misconceiving
misconceiving it into a kind of
absorption or focusing practice but um
how do you focus on your mental
state which is the third saana how do
you focus on feeling which are not
Sensations yeah how do you focus on
because it says there uh if if uh uh
feelings were Sensations then why does
the satiana says I know when I
experience a feeling of the flesh I know
where and I experience a feeling that's
not of the flesh meaning it's not a
sensation uhhuh so um how can you uh
focus on the four noble truths which are
also uh in the in the Sati how can you
focus on the seven enlightment factors
how can you focus on the five hindrances
so all of these things are on that same
level of a peripheral context and
mindfulness of the body is exactly the
same it's it's it's nothing special so
it's the purpose of for example the
mindfulness of the postures is like I
said I mean I've been talking the whole
time I haven't forgotten the fact that I
am sitting even though the mind is going
in all sorts of different directions so
it's why why
then why is it uh why would it be
beneficial to have that memory of the
body there let's say the posture that
it's in or um something like the auba
practice or mhm
breathing why would that be beneficial
if it's not a now that we've clarified
that it's not a focus thing um yeah so
now that we clarified that body is not
an object in front of you that you
attend to but is itself a context that
one can recollect which is one of the
right Recollections so now you're asking
why is that part of the actual Dharma
and why is that wholesome yeah
H any ideas
anyone it um
well you can see that this thing that is
like this kind of context of being
embodied you could
say um it doesn't require you putting it
um it doesn't require you putting it
there it's there whether you're kind
of like attending to it or not um so if
you kind of keep that in the background
then whatever you do whatever you see
whatever you think of throughout the day
is put into
this
um trying to put this in my own words
instead of just using the buzzword
but you're
um I I I guess it can just kind of show
you that it is not something that is
your doing in a way it's not um it's not
dependent upon your putting it there and
why is it what happens when you don't
have a that type of
a that type of
perspective then you you kind of just
Overlook it and take it on as
like for granted like oh this
is I guess you kind of you kind of put
yourself there
there
um and you you don't
um you don't see it as being something
that is necessary for whatever you're
engaging in I guess so for instance like
if you're not kind of aware of there
being a
tongue and you're like eating you might
kind of act in a heedless way just kind of
of act in a heedless way just kind of
like taking on that taste for instance
whereas so so when it
says um harboring sensual desire
internally in relation to that Haring
the hindrances internally when a person
focuses when a person is just thinking
about what's in front of them like the
wild cult M how does um actually
establish in the context like it says
there asking the horse asking himself
what does a trainer want me to do today
how does that fix that situation of
being overcome by sensual desire
aversion and so
on well it's kind of taking a different
it's including that internal aspect
within your kind of contemplation but
what what happens when it's not
included well in that case then it is
internal and you're kind of you're there
essentially like it's
a you kind of become susceptible to
whatever that is susceptible to yeah so
the point being you don't need to um
explicitly be heedless or or or um do
anything immoral or do anything bad not
having mindfulness in and of itself
opens the way for greed diversion and
delusion so it's
um the the fact of regaining that
perspective over your
experience if the P perspective is
properly established any of these things like
established any of these things like
what is sensual desire can you be
sensually obsessed with an object if you
have perspective you can't because sensor
perspective you can't because sensor
desire is precisely the loss of
perspective it's not the pleasure of the
object it's not the the perception of it
it's when you all of these hindrances
actually it's not the things that are
that arose in your mind it's when you
become absorbed in it mhm yeah and
absorption and the right mindfulness
that's a contradiction yeah so anything
then that becomes that you become
absorbed in automatically introduces one
of the five hindrances mhm even if it's
a mental thing that has nothing to do
with uh
the usual things that you perceive in
the world if it's just a mental
perception during a absorption
experience desire that the principle of
Desire the principle of wanting the
principle of appropriation is there for
as long as you lack perspective in
regard to that thing yeah so that's why
ironically with this view of absorption
many people would say you are attached
or you're sort of indulging in this um
this object that has arisen but
actually the peace comes from the
opposite direction when you withdraw
yourself from anything that your
attention could have been AB
um uh taken by while the attention is
still there you don't destroy the
attention but you simply
you basically develop this Vantage
Point that's what you could say that's
what mindfulness is mindfulness is like
a vantage point and while everything
else is happening here well that vantage
point is kept so it doesn't matter the
even the content of what's here you
realize all the problems arose because
you were here it doesn't matter what
even if it's a good thing that was down
here if you are there there is sensal
desire aversion yeah restlessness
craving of some kind craving for more of
this pleasant experience that I think is
wholesome but because I'm absorbed in it
well the principle of of wanting more
pleasure is still there and that's
what's UNH
wholesome now I have a question suppose
somebody follows the discussion so far
and they see okay mindfulness is not
getting Rost in that direction but this
establishing this context or this
spiritual awareness as we have said so
they try to practice that and they say
it's too vast it's too spacious to just
dwell in that context there there's
nothing really there for for for me to
hold on to I need something more
specific to Anchor my mind because I'm
too busy too distracted it might work
for one or two minutes and then I'm just
spaced out for the for the next two
hours would it not be better to
introduce some object in front of me
that I can fiddle around with to to
Anchor my mind in that direction first
right which is a very
idea um you know Tau on meditation so
there's this there's this presumed gradual
this there's this presumed gradual
development of mindfulness there um but
um there are some risks connected with
that because you are already moving away
from the context so if if somebody finds
themselves sort of in between these two
domains what can they practically do to
strengthen that context and that
understanding without falling back again
in the in the old groove of of wanting
to be with something in front of you
because you think that is how your mind
comes down yeah so what what do you
think well I think it's a general thing
that we take the Buddha teaching qu the
other way around like we start with like
meditation sitting and then we go oh
maybe I should maybe moderate my eating
maybe my sleep as well or what's my
intention is actually but still I'm
sitting there and and then we come to
the precept maybe one day and I think if
one person find himself like that this
context this mindfulness is too spacious
for him it's just because he's doing
actively things that prevent him to
discern that mindfulness that is already
there so the things is
like he
should this person should like realize
that it's not so much about doing
certain things actively right now but
it's restraining myself for doing things
that prevent me to discern what my is
what we what we are talking about so
what so what does somebody more more
practically perhaps need need to
restrain because this context as you
actually said in in in in the beginning
it's not that you magically lose it in
in a sense it is because I make certain
choices that that that that context um
that one Falls away so to speak from the
context so how does one prevent that
from happening because that is how you
can have the have the openness and the
spaciousness without falling into the
absorption of the other direction yeah
not to miss the if openness and SP is
again it's like um it's
a it's something that you already have
some experience of it's just that the
theme of it is not the right one it's
like just mundane things
mhm so where so so so where would be the
so so what would the person then then
practically do to to sustain that
context
well it depends where this person is but
let's say like someone that never heard
anything and start right now it will be
like respecting the precept and then
sense restraint and then so on like kind
of the gradual training
and yeah and also like if this person
like something that I kind of hear a lot
as well is like oh yeah I need these
people to meditate I need this group
meditation and stuff like that and
that's also like kind of something that
someone should consider that if he's
looking for some else to be there in
order to meditate that is because he's
looking for reward again he's hoping for
something to to to an experence to arise
yeah and also
um can you keep the precepts if you're
not mindful yeah that's the whole point now
mindful yeah that's the whole point now
yeah yeah so um that is actually when
when it feels like these uh Force poanas
are too difficult
um because actually there's this suta
where the Buddha takes even months
actually not not lay people and he
instructs them instructs them in five
things that are basic for their training
and none of those five things are the
force ofas mhm it's uh the precepts
sense restraint moderation and eating uh
restraining their speech and developing
Right View developing right right views
yeah um I I think it says that dwell in
seclusion this instruction for new legal
en
forth but but yeah so it's it's it's
along those same lines it it doesn't say
develop satiana yeah so because satiana
if you look at the graduate training
that comes already when the person is in
the position of to abandon the five
hindrances because yes um the context of
the body feeling mind all these things
technically you could recognize them for
a moment because they are there but
realistically speaking if you're not
established in these prerequisites it
will be dissipating very quickly because
you haven't even
discerned um even the mental choices not
just the bodily and verbal choices the
mental choices that you make that uh
cause that context to dissipate and then
it feels like it just goes by itself
because you're not able to even see your
own choices of greed diversion and
delusion that are um making it fizzled
out that that you are making basically
yeah so so um that would be the first
Direction if you don't have mindfulness
you simply won't be able to to uh keep
sensor strength and that's what the S to
say sensor strength cannot be done
without mindfulness because it's not
about like predetermining a certain set
of behaviors that I will never do like I
will never look at this I will never
look at that as it says it's
specifically you need to have an
awareness of whether um states of
longing or rsion might arise as a result
of what you look at or listen to and so
on which means you already need to have
a degree of mindfulness if you're just
absorbed you won't be able to tell uh
which things
are um harmful for you to attend to and
which things are not so mindfulness
would already be involved in in that
that entire practice and uh for someone
who is starting the training yeah that
would be more than enough um that would
keep them occupied 24/7 basically yeah
uh because then you have this desire
okay should sit down and focus on an
object okay but are you are you allowing
yourself to like why did you take that
for granted why didn't you um if you
just jumped at that thought means you
already lost the context a long time ago
because you would see that there is just
a some kind of craving involved there
yeah so once's thoughts are also objects
in front of you that's another thing
that that we should clarify we're not
just talking about candle flames and
pictures of the Buddha on the wall or on
the shrine now even your own thoughts or
mantras or or ideas that you dwell on
right thoughts because as it test I
think sensed cognized and and so on that
is still all partaking in that direction
and so there will be a context to that
actually that's a that's a good one the
Mantra is like Father father just
replace it with Buddha Buddha and it's
it's exactly the same thing so
um it's uh yeah even if you find like
the wholesome thoughts let's say you
discern I don't know um Au subba for
example which is like the Buddha says
this is a beneficial practice and then
people do it as a form of visualization
like I need to have these images
constantly just uh like locking my mind
into these mental things that are
explored by the mind as it says there
yeah so various stages of decomposing
bodies and stuff like this and then you
like keep bringing that image up until like
keep bringing that image up until like
it stays there and then magically that
gets conceived as the St as a state of
samadi but um it's uh it's not even it's
not that at all even if like I said even
if it's a good thing for you to absorb
yourself in like I said being on the
level of objects is the problem it's not
what you are uh like attending to is the
fact that you're attending without
mindfulness that's the problem so if you
attend to anything even the most
superficially wholesome thoughts but you
don't have that Vantage Point that's uh
at the back of that peripheral to all
that then um to some extent uh the five
entrances are still there your mind is
still mired in some form of sensual
desire aversion and actually if you look
closely at these these um absor
absorption practic that people do it's
actually quite um it's it's quite
stressful like they themselves would say
um after some time like you get tired of
of uh yeah even of the pleasant
experiences they would say like oh the
first J you have this pleasure and then
at some point it's just too much that's
not how it works in in the suas um yeah
like it's quite interesting because like
this kind of absorption practice like
you come first time first session you
see 10 minutes or that's enough that
kind of and then you do it again next
day and then one week later you 10
minutes in the morning 10 minutes in the
evening m 1 year later you find yourself
doing 1 hour in the morning 1 hour in
the evening 2 years later you do 10 days
Retreat 10 hours a day but that's
exactly like smoking or any single
addiction basically you just need more
and more and more and more and more not
realizing that that attitude is actually
what's actually very stressful and the
thing is you're chasing something the
whole time you're chasing something
whereas this is more
like the direction of chasing things see
it's not like oh just let go relax in
the present moment and and don't
strive letting go of chasing takes
effort it's something you have to
discern like the the attitude of not
chasing anything
requires like the most deep penetrated
wisdom it's not like you can't just
decide okay I will just sit down and I
will not crave for anything it requires
that because on the most fundamental
level your being right that is already
there's already is seeking or striving
involved in in in in in that one one is
maintaining one's existence so to speak
and this is about learning to not do
that and for as long as there isn't that
vantage point that we're describing the
seeking is there automatically like
that's all it takes you don't need to
think to yourself let me seek something
it's just the directionality the way the
Mind goes when there isn't that
background is already towards
expectations and anticipations and
desires yeah perhaps we should clear up
also how this feds in with what we
earlier discussed in the context of
yonis Manara because there are these two
directions right yeah um so factor for
the Right View y only Manara but
obviously yo is not mindfulness but
mindfulness is also not Auto
automatically endowed with with
attending from that origin so to speak
so we should perhaps now bring them
together and then see if we can make a
move from what this right how this right
mindfulness then results in right samadi
yeah so um that's that would be the the
factor that would turn that would allow
you to go from just a
mundane uh way of mindfulness just the
remembering the things that you're
supposed to do throughout the day would
bring you now to actually the Buddhist
teaching your because it's it's now more
of um acute
lishment where um the context is is is
not just another thought that you have
there uh about something in the world is
these relevant things to your existence
that are at the background always like
the the supermarket thing that you're
supposed to do this that's not there
always like that's that specific
situation but the body feelings mind and
phenomena those things are always is
there so those things are even behind
like even on a deeper layer than these
mundane types of mindfulness that you
would have yeah so you would see uh
whether it's where whether it's that
being at the grocery store whether it's
sitting down at in a in a room empty
room um body feelings mind and phenomena
have to be there and that's the origin
of anything else that you might attend
to so when when um
when that y aspect is developed only
then can you get into that dimension of
radi which is by the way that's that's
the the whole point of uh of the noble
AAL path as it says is um the
cultivation of Sati the cultivation of
forti panas leads to samadi and um
samadi would based on what we're
discussing it it becomes clear that um
develop that direction would just take
you exactly to what it says here like
the mind would become totally
independent even of its own thoughts
even of what's explored by the mental
faculty you have a
broader uh context than that which is
the body that's always there the feeling
that's always there those things are
behind or underneath anything that you
might uh perceive and then when that
recognition becomes so strengthened that
um there is no need for you to even
refresh it uh you know periodically that you had
it uh you know periodically that you had
to do it before like even if you just
totally try to forget it you can't
because you see that the experience of
forgetting is something that's explored
by the mind which is second to the body
that's already there when you say behind
or underneath something that I find
useful to think about that is say you
have like a um a structured set of t
tasks so you're looking for a nail
because like you're looking for a nail
because you need to replace or you need
to fix a paintbrush because you're
trying to paint a room because you're
planning to sell this house for for
instance you can be looking for that
nail and completely forget that you're
doing it to F fix a paintbrush yeah or
you can kind of have the paintbrush in
mind but forget that you're painting the
room but kind of you can kind of see
things and this kind structured way but
I guess the point being no well I guess
I was kind of stacking it up like this
but you said below not that it matters
to too much but like there will be the
for Sati panas underlying whatever task
you're doing so that's kind of you would
you would have to work towards that so
so that that structure is there right
just in ordinary situations but then you
want to push it further by I in the
house right right and until at some
point you have to realize well because
having been born I'm subject to old age
sickness and death uh losing what I now
take to be mine is unpleasant which is
bound to happen right I have to put up
with all sorts of stuff that I don't
want I can't always get the things that
I do want in short I'm AF pray to
suffering that so we so somebody has to
basically go if they find themselves Now
searching for new then they can all the
way to that context yeah right although
of course it's not that um it would take
time to like find it it's already there
it's just that not like an intellectual
exercise oh am why am I really searching
for the mail oh it's cuz my father when
I was 12 no no because because then you
get lost in in all sorts of well that's
explored by the mind you're getting
absorbed in that so no it's it's um well
again the same direction where people
start noting things like sitting sitting
walking walking go in that direction but without
walking go in that direction but without
trying to block now like whatever you're
thinking about and whatever you're
perceiving don't try to replace what you
were doing instead see those things
happening on happening on two different
levels which means you won't be able to
keep noting constantly in your mind
because that's that that's going to
become an object but you have that
awareness it's like a 1% of of your
that's why we call it peripheral it's
kind of like a peripheral
vision um like you know I can be a A
Ware of uh my
hands here I'm not looking at them while
I'm looking at you and I'm Discerning
the aspects of your face but I know that
my hand is still right here at the same
time so if I now start doing this now
something else becomes peripheral so if
you start focusing on sitting sitting
walking walking well the actual context
is now behind that the actual
mindfulness is now behind that yeah so
that context is also not fixed it does
depend on what it is that one is
deliberately attending to is part of the
mindfulness so that's why you set it up
so you have a choice that's called
satiana setting up of mindfulness so you
have a a choice of which of these things
you you want to use and all of them
serve the same purpose and that's why
exactly sometimes in the sutas it
wouldn't even matter um things that that
are seemingly not related to like the
for Noble Truths they would still um
serve as an instrument for uh
establishing the mind like you have
these huge lists of things in the sutas
the four Brahma viharas you have the
four Great elements you have um the
casinas you have
the uh sometimes even the Buddha would
say when for for monks like when you see
a woman uh regard her as your mother or
your sister or as your daughter so that
censal desire won't arise yeah uh
recollection of the Buddha damama
recollection of virtue recollection of
the dasas uh recollection of rotting
bones um like any basically anything
that you can anything that serves on
that um that can be established on that
peripheral level because again it's what
matters is not the content what matters
is the fact that you have that Vantage
Point yeah above everything else and
that's actually the unification of
mind uh which is the the characteristic
of samadi eag it's not one pointedness
as in I became so dependent on what is
seen heard cognized and explored by the
mental faculty that I now don't see
anything else it's you became so aware
of that um that background that
peripheral aspect that endures there
that now like I said
before uh you you need to not you now
you don't even need to make the effort
to remember it because in death scenario
in a sense nothing is left out yeah
right so that is the one pointedness
quote unquote it talks about a totality
of experience that doesn't allow in a
room for something to be outside of it
which is a different kind of one poess
than focusing on one thing to the
exclusion of everything else and that
how somebody would help you to see but
is some B which is the simultaneous
dependence of two things you will be
able to see then that um see the the
point of the point of view or the setup
that occurs when you're absorbed is
exactly what won't allow you to actually
see that anous dependence and that's why
people who practice absorption think is
like seeing a sequence of factors
arising but the dhama is timeless as the
B said so having that setup of two
things enduring at the same time the
context and what you're directly
attendant to you you you start to
realize that uh none of those two
directions can
fundamentally uh be taken as yours in
the sense of like you can choose to call
it yours but uh how can it really be
yours if it's if if it depends on
something else yeah so I was just going
to ask that like why is it that rightly
Discerning this principle of dependent
origination is going to uproot or a face
that sense of
self this is kind of what I was trying
to say earlier was if you
have kind of both aspects you have
perspective on both then you're not
either yeah you can't be if you are one
but you see that that one depends on
something else which which you're not
that one to cut it if you the other one
it's the same thing yeah so so so you
you get minced in between basically the
the thing is when there isn't that
mindfulness on established on that right
level even if you choose to say this is
not mine what you're actually taking as
mine what you're actually taking as
yours is that sort of point of view that
that Observer but see that's right whether
Observer but see that's right whether
you realize it or not it's not even like
a matter of
choice but that mindfulness precisely is
supposed to come before that Observer
that's the whole point of it like The
Observer what's explored by the mind you
would start to see even that thing that
I regarded as
myself because you have expanded your
perspective this vantage point now
allows you to see wait that's actually
just another phenomenon mhm whereas
before that's that phenomenon was still
a phenomenon but because you were
focused on what was over there it seemed
like it was more than just the
phenomenon this one is more special than
the others that sense of self yeah yeah
can we say that uh as long as someone
tried to make the effort to look
something as not
mine that I mean like seeing things as
not mine should not it's a recognition
that doesn't take effort yeah it's not
something that is actively done and and
the five Aggregates um which are the
main things that that you have to
understand they not yours five
Aggregates are never what you're looking
at or at least that's not the aspect
that matters the aspect of the five
Aggregates is that um background aspect
of it that's always there so the feeling
that enduring while you're focused on
this the perception that's enduring the
ideas the Notions that are enduring
Consciousness fundamentally is always
that background and if you think you're
watching your object your Consciousness
as an object which people would
sometimes think that's not Consciousness
anymore no consciousness is what's uh
doing the watching and like sometimes
there's a view okay when you have
developed your focusing skills then you
can turn your attention to see
consciousness itself but you can't see
Consciousness itself first of all and
second of all it's not later that you're
supposed to do that the practice starts
with putting the point of view in
perspective yeah so to say oh let me
focus on this for a little while to a
step and then I'll switch it over that's
already Mission the point yeah you start
by switching it over that would have
been the right my and then if you go in
the direction of concentration by that
time like your mind is already
constricted so then anything you look at
even if you have increased powers of
observation all of it is coming through
that directionality of me looking at it
yeah even more than before you want to
see that that attention is basically
also there on its own it's not you
attending F fundamentally and that's why
as well um maybe the last thing we can
clear up
is uh there can be no uh mindfulness by
itself like in the context of the path
cuz usually it's like okay I start with
mindfulness and that will take me to
Right View but it's the other way around
it's knowing what you're supposed to
recollect knowing how you're supposed to
recollect knowing what the context is
that's that is what allows you to be
properly mindful um so actually it's
more of like
um instead of okay I have my idea of
mindfulness let me start doing it now so
I can get the result of stream entry or
whatever you're aiming for it should
should be by understanding what
mindfulness is to begin with I will be
able to reach stream ENT or what not so
it's like
um let's say like your your mindfulness
practice is like your the your Technique
or your form with which you do a certain
physical exercise and if just the first day you
exercise and if just the first day you
see somebody else grabbing the weight
and you go and do the same okay now I'm
just G to do this until I get strong and
you never actually took the time to
perfect your form how you actually do
the exercise well you're not even doing
it properly M and that's that's the that
that would be the which is going to
backfire at some point yeah yeah so that
would be the point with um the whole
practice it's like first of all in order
to gain the right
view your goal should be learn how to do
the exercise properly to begin with but
see the thing is that's pouring that's
not as fun as you know grabbing the five
5B dumbbell and really focusing on like
okay what's my shoulder positioning am I
and then okay I'm just going to grab 50
lbs and then I'm just going to cheat
however way I want yeah um so that's the
that's why people don't want to do it
because well it's a form of impatience
basically but it's it ends up backfiring
as you said yeah it's in Pence and also
like people want to do the practice in
their own way the way they like it the
way they kind of it feels good it's nice
it's kind of like I heard like one time
I was reading a book A book and there
was this teacher saying like oh yeah you
just take from like all the tradition
and you make your own pizza but like if
you never learn to bake a pizzas that's
going to taste terrible like you put
like fish and then whatever else on top
and it's just never going to be a pizza
B yeah so you you actually need to
develop your own criteria as to what's
right and wrong before you can practice
because there is no guarantee otherwise
that that you yeah and but those
criteria obviously have to come from the
actual right instruction yeah yeah so
it's it has to be a combination of both
but it's always that um that well that's
another context you can develop like I
don't understand that's a mindfulness that you
understand that's a mindfulness that you
keep and if you lose
that you will start then taking for
granted things that feel good to you or
seems like it helps mhm or ignoring the
fact that as a Buddha said we are
enveloped within ignorance like within
an egg so you can't
see you don't see the way out even if it
seems the way out like the way out for
you until you're at least assult upon
it's not the way out it's some form of
improving what you feel but it's not a
form of actual um disowning actual uh
ending of craving so it's it's uh
it's um that's an that's one of the
mindfulness say that you that a person
should move first and that's why Faith
as well is the first of the faculties
mindfulness is actually not the first of
the five faculties is Faith and faith is
basically that um recognition that I'm
always willing to give up what I think
is a practice if I come across the
instruction of wherever I put Faith in
saying that that's wrong that's what say
this